Guide to the William Wallace Booth Papers, 1922-1973 AIS.1973.23
ULS Archives & Special Collections
William Wallace Booth Papers
1922-1973
1941-1973
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Booth, William Wallace
AIS.1973.23
11.3 Linear Feet (9 boxes)
The William Wallace Booth Papers are comprised of correspondence, documents, memoranda, minutes, and reports related to Booth's activities as a trustee of the University of Pittsburgh; an officer and director of the Oakland Corporation; and as a founder of the Aspen Corporation.
Access Restrictions
No restrictions.
Previous Citation
William Wallace Booth Papers, 1922-1973, AIS.1973.23, Archives Service Center, University of Pittsburgh
Scope and Content Notes
The William Wallace Booth Papers are divided into three subgroups: University of Pittsburgh; Oakland Corporation; and Aspen Corporation. The University of Pittsburgh materials date from 1936-1973, but are primarily concerned with his time on the Board of Trustees, Executive Committee, and various other committees, 1941-1968. Booth joined the Oakland Corporation, a private development company designed to preserve and develop the university areas in Pittsburgh, circa 1961, where he served as an officer and director. In 1965 he helped form the Aspen Corporation, a private company that searched for legal documents on clients' behalf. The bulk of the materials in the Booth papers consist of correspondence, reports, memoranda, and minutes.
Biography
William Wallace Booth was born in Allegheny, Pennsylvania, on November 2, 1896 to Harry and Ella Wallace. His college career was interrupted by World War I where he served as a pilot in the U.S. Air Corps from 1917-1919. On returning home Booth finished his B.S. in Economics at the University of Pittsburgh in 1920. In 1922 he completed an LL.B. and was admitted to the Pennsylvania bar later that year. He began his practice in Pittsburgh in 1922, and went on to join the firm of Reed, Smith, Shaw, and Clay in 1935 where he worked until his retirement in 1969.
His alumni work with the University of Pittsburgh began in 1940 when he served on the Alumni Committee on Trustees' Elections. He was a member of the Alumni Council from 1941-1947, the Board of Trustees from 1941-1969, and the Executive Committee from 1955-1968.
William Booth married Adelaide Skelton Lanz in 1925, and the couple had three children: William Wallace, James Youngson, and Cynthia Skelton. On October 21, 1986, William Booth died of heart failure; he was 89 years old.
Arrangement
This collection is divided into three subgroups with numerous associated series:
Subgroup 1. University of Pittsburgh, 1922-1973
Subgroup 2. Oakland Corporation
Subgroup 3. Aspen Corporation
Architecture; Real estate developers -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; University of Pittsburgh; Health services administration -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Education; Universities and colleges -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Real estate development -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; University of Pittsburgh; Booth, William Wallace; Aspen Corporation; Oakland Corporation; University of Pittsburgh. Medical Center; University of Pittsburgh. Board of Trustees
- University of Pittsburgh, 1922-1973; 1941-1968; 1.
  Scope and Content Notes
  The University of Pittsburgh subgroup dates from 1922-1973, but are primarily concerned with William Booth's time on the Board of Trustees, Executive Committee, and various other committees, 1941-1968. The subgroup includes by-laws, charters, correspondence, financial records, legislative acts, memoranda, minutes, newspaper clippings, and reports. The primary focus of this subgroup is University committees and it covers no less than fifteen committees including a variety of special and permanent committees of the Board of Trustees. There is also material on various health groups affiliated with the university as well as smaller subject files on campus development, the alumni association, Booth's law school reunions, chancellors, and other university related organizations.
  - Charter, Legislative Acts, Public Documents, and By-Laws, 1930-1971; I.
    - Charters of the University of Pittsburgh with amendments, 1949 and 1960; legislative acts and public documents related to the University of Pittsburgh, 1936; By-laws of the Board of Trustees, 1930, 1949-1964; By Laws of the University of Pittsburgh of the Commonwealth System of Higher Education, 1969-1971, 1930-1971 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Minutes of the Board of Trustees and Executive Committee of the Board of Trustees, 1940-1973; II.
    Includes minutes for Executive Committee Meetings, Trustees Annual Board Meetings, Fall Board Meetings, Winter Board Meeting, Spring Board Meetings, Special Meetings of the Executive Committee, Board of Trustees Meetings.
    Folders are arranged by school year (July through April of the next year) and as such date ranges have been left blank unless they differ from the school year date. Beginning with the Winter Meeting Of the Trustees, December 9, 1958, minutes of all meetings, with a few exceptions, are individually bound.
    - Meeting minutes for 1940/41 and 1941/42, 1941-1942 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Meeting minutes for 1942/43 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Meeting minutes for 1943/44 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Meeting minutes for 1944/45 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Meeting minutes for 1945/46 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Meeting minutes for 1946/47 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Meeting minutes for 1947/48 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Meeting minutes for 1948/49 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Meeting minutes for 1949/50 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Meeting minutes for 1950/51 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Meeting minutes for 1951/52 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Meeting minutes for 1951/52 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Meeting minutes for 1952/53 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Meeting minutes for 1953/54 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Docket for Meeting of the Board of Trustees, December 8, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 15)
      Includes: Floor plans George Hubbard Clapp Hall and a map of University of Pittsburgh with surrounding property.
    - Meeting minutes for 1954/55 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Meeting minutes for 1955/56 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Meeting minutes for 1956/57 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Meeting minutes for 1957/58 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Meeting minutes for 1958/59 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Meeting minutes for 1959/60-1962/63, May 11, 1959 - May 14, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Meeting minutes for 1962/63 and 1963/64, May 14, 1963 - July 25, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Meeting minutes for 1963/64-1968/69, September 10, 1963 - June 16, 1969 (Box 3, Folder 22a)
    - Meeting minutes for 1969/70, September 9, 1969 - February 23, 1970 (Box 3, Folder 23)
    - Meeting minutes for 1969/70, April 14, 1970 - June 9, 1970 (Box 3, Folder 24)
    - Meeting minutes for 1970/71-1972/73, July 14, 1970 - April 10, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 24a)
    - Resolutions, 1963-1965 (Box 4, Folder 25)
      - Roger S. Ahlbrandt - Expressing the board's gratitude for his service as a trustee, 1.
      - Authorizing the city of Pittsburgh to construct a water line through university property, 2.
      - Authorizing purchase of Bellefield Avenue property, 3.
      - Approving the awarding of 923 degrees, August 11, 1963; 4.
      - Approving the awarding of 991degrees, August 6, 1965; 5.
      - Authorizing the sale of property to GSA, 6.
      - David L. Lawrence - Expressing the board's gratitude for his service as a trustee, 7.
      - William D. McClelland - Expressing the board's gratitude for his service as a trustee, 8.
      - Authorizing university to participate in MPC Corporation, 9.
      - Authorization purchase of National Union Insurance Company Building, 10.
      - Charles B. Nutting - Resolution in appreciation of his service to the university, 11.
      - Walter J. Rome - Expressing the board's appreciation for his service as a trustee, 12.
      - Rev. Dr. Howard C. Scharre - Expressing the board's appreciation for his service as a trustee, 13.
      - Authorizing sale of land in Virgin Gorda, 14.
      - Resolution to authorize borrowing against state appropriations for the current quarter, April 1, 1965 - June 30, 1965; 15.
    - Index of meeting minutes for 1956/57 through 1960/61 (Box 4, Folder 26)
    - Index of meeting minutes for 1961/62 through 1967/68 (Box 4, Folder 26b)
  - Committees of the Board of Trustees, 1940-1973; III.
    - Athletics Committee, 1.
      - Correspondence, 1952-1967 (Box 4, Folder 27)
        Thanking the Masonic Fund Society for allowing Pitt to use the lot behind the Temple for women's athletics, September 27, 1952. Objection from Booth to Stanton C. Crawford regarding a press announcement that Michelosen's firing was unanimous, November 26, 1965. Letter from the chairman to a committee member stating the committee's consensus on Michelosen, November 27, 1965. Letter from the ABC NCAA press director critical of Pitt's sparse number of football scholarships, January 27, 1967.
      - Correspondence regarding professional sports use of Pitt Stadium and plan for a municipal authority to assume stadium, 1956-1959 (Box 4, Folder 28)
        Operation proposed by V.C.A. Scully, CPA, November 13, 1956. NCAA objections, February 11, 1958. Under a Steeler letterhead to the Public Auditorium Authority conditions under which the Steeler will lease Pitt Stadium, March 19, 1958. Litchfield's letter to the NCAA informing the association that Pitt will lease the stadium and assuring Pitt will maintain its standards in athletics, March 26, 1958. Indication that Litchfield is beginning to doubt the practicality of pro sports in the stadium because of traffic congestion, April 25, 1958. The use of the stadium for professional sports is a dead issue, April 20, 1959.
      - Legal documents regarding stadium lease (Box 4, Folder 29)
      - Memoranda regarding budget, 1957-1959 (Box 4, Folder 30)
        Budget Reports, December 31, 1957 and March 18, 1959. Request for additional funds for repair and alteration, February 13, 1958.
      - Memoranda regarding general subjects, 1958-1959 (Box 4, Folder 31)
        Study of how the trimester would affect the intercollegiate sports program, January 14, 1958. Proposal to acquire the Oakland Lutheran Cemetery, church inquiry as to Pitt's intentions, February 12, 1958. Recommendation from the athletic director to the chancellor for more athletic scholarships, March 20, 1959. Report on the reorganization of the physical education department, March 26, 1959. Reply to the evaluation women's and men's physical education faculty efficiency, April 17 & 20, 1959. Chancellor's recommendations to the Trustees concerning physical education, athletic policy and operations, June 22, 1959.
      - Memoranda regarding professional sports use of Pitt Stadium, 1958-1959 (Box 4, Folder 32)
        Objections of T.J. Hamilton, February 6, 1958. NCAA policy statement on college professional relationship, February 12, 1958. Legal opinion that rent from professional teams is not taxable income, March 4, 1958. Statement by Litchfield to Hamilton on the pros and cons of having professional sports in the stadium, April 15, 1958 Comments regarding Hamilton's plans to revamp the stadium and related parking problems, December 30, 1958. Hamilton's support of conversion plan based on a study by the engineering consulting firm of Ford, Bacon, & Davis, April 1, 1959. Litchfield's recommendation to the Trustees against converting the stadium, March 2, 1959.
      - Minutes, October 8, 1963 (Box 4, Folder 33)
      - Newspaper Clippings regarding firing of Michelson; New York Times Sports column on Hamilton (Box 4, Folder 34)
      - Subject files, 1955-1958
        - City County Stadium Study Committee, Report on Proposed new stadium, September 15, 1958; 1. (Box 4, Folder 35)
        - Conversion of Pitt Stadium to a municipal stadium, 2.
        - Scholarship Program, 1955-1958; 3.
        - Speech - T.J. Hamilton urging conversion of Pitt Stadium to a municipal stadium, 4.
    - By-Law Revision Committee, 2.
      - Correspondence, 1955-1960 (Box 4, Folder 36)
        Noting that Dr. Litchfield had recommended changes in the administrative structure of the university and changes in the bylaws were thus necessary, October 24, 1955. Various correspondence between members of the committee their comments on issues before the committee, 1955-1959. Comment that the committee's work is complete, March 9, 1960. Recommendation to insert in the bylaws that announcement of tenure be made on March 15, not April 1, May 14, 1960.
      - Memoranda - suggestions as to principles of tenure (Box 4, Folder 37)
      - Minutes for May 5, 1958 and October 6, 1959 and for the Joint Meeting with the Nominating Committee, December 16, 1966, 1958-1966 (Box 4, Folder 38)
      - Subject file - "Report of the Joint (Faculty Trustee Administration) Committee on Faculty Participation in Policy Making" (Box 4, Folder 39)
      - Subject file - Proposed revisions in the by-laws, 1955-1968 (Box 4, Folder 40)
    - Facilities Committee, 3.
      - Minutes, May 3, 1971 (Box 4, Folder 41)
    - Finance Committees, 4.
      Note the 1949 correspondence which indicates a change in the committee's function and responsibilities. Most of the succeeding correspondence consists of request, recommendations, and reports from the financial advisors. Meeting notices appear on an irregular basis.
      - Correspondence, 1949 (Box 4, Folder 42)
        Recommendations on proposed by laws changing the committee's structure, March 9, 1949. Extract from the meeting of March 8, at which by law changes were discussed, June 4, 1949. Comparison of changes with present (old) by-laws, April 13, 1949. Mellon Bank, by letter, advises Booth that it has recently been appointed financial advisor to the university; in addition there is correspondence which either deals with the by law question or is from the bank requesting permission to sell recently donated stock, December 23, 1949.
      - Correspondence, 1950 (Box 4, Folder 43)
        Letter with attachments, reviewing University of Pittsburgh's financial status; most of this correspondence consists of request from the bank to authorize sale of recently donated stock, March 10, 1950.
      - Correspondence, 1951 (Box 4, Folder 44)
        Request of the bank to sell recently donated stock and a few letters discussing investments.
      - Correspondence, 1952 (Box 4, Folder 45)
        Discussion of investments; request from bank to sell recently donated stock, December 2, 1952.
      - Correspondence, 1953-1954 (Box 4, Folder 46)
        Review of university investments; bank request to sell recently donated stock, March 4, 1954.
      - Correspondence, 1955-1956 (Box 4, Folder 47)
        Reference to the fact that the Executive Committee authorized liquidation of the George H. Clapp Fund; requests by the bank to sell recently donated stock, October 22, 1956.
      - Correspondence, 1957-1958 (Box 4, Folder 48)
        Bank request to sell recently donated stock.
      - Correspondence, 1959 (Box 4, Folder 49)
        Recommendation from the bank to liquidate some stock to acquire cash for the purchasing of the Webster Hall Hotel, June 16, 1959. On September 28, 1959 the finance committee decided to sell low high priced common stock, November 24, 1959.
      - Correspondence, 1960-1964 (Box 4, Folder 50)
        Letters addressed to Booth, as a Finance Committee member requesting authorization to sell recently received stock or to transfer stock already owned.
      - Memoranda, 1941-1971 (Box 4, Folder 51)
        Establishment of a common agency account for endowment and investment funds; legal opinion by Booth and resolution to establish. Explanation of major budget variance for the eight months ended March, 1967. Proposed Special Fund raising projects for the university, December 22, 1971. Resolution regarding $2,985,000 DHUD Bonds, 1965. Statement by the financial advisor on the status of University investments, June 30, 1959. Resolution to authorize borrowing pending receipt of state appropriation, for the 1965 quarter, October 1, 1965 - December 31, 1965. Securities which may be converted into cash, December 31, 1941. Securities sold, redeemed, or purchased by University officers between June and September, 1949, November 30, 1951.
      - Minutes, 1949-1951 (Box 4, Folder 52)
      - Minutes, 1952-1961 (Box 4, Folder 53)
      - Minutes, 1963-1967 (Box 4, Folder 54)
      - Budget - Income and expenditures; estimates of income and budget; and estimate of receipts and disbursements, 1956-1961 (Box 4, Folder 55a)
      - Budget - Balance sheets and statements of operations, 1958-1960 (Box 4, Folder 55b)
      - Budget - Financial statements, 1960-1963 (Box 4, Folder 55c)
      - Budget - Financial statements for 1962-1963 and a report on gifts received for the fiscal year 1961, 1961-1963 (Box 4, Folder 55d)
      - Budget - Financial statements and evaluation, 1964; summary of financial projections for the 1964/65 year; and ten year budget forecast, circa January, 1965, 1964-1965 (Box 4, Folder 55e)
      - Budget - Review of July 31, 1966 financial statements, October 28, 1966 (Box 4, Folder 55f)
      - Budget - Operating budget 1966/67 (Box 4, Folder 55g)
      - Budget - Final operating budget 1968/69, October 17, 1968 (Box 4, Folder 55h)
      - Budget - Budget report (preliminary) 1970/71, May 13, 1970 (Box 4, Folder 55i)
      - Budget - General Assembly of the Commonwealth of Pennsylvania, presentation of the University Budget 1970/71 (Box 4, Folder 55j)
      - Budget - General Assembly of the Commonwealth of Pennsylvania, presentation of the University Budget 1972/73 and 1973/74 (Box 4, Folder 55k)
      - General and endorsement account statements, March-April, 1949 (Box 5, Folder 56)
        The general and endorsement account statements files were prepared by the Trust Department of the Mellon National Bank and Trust Company, the Trust agent of the University of Pittsburgh. Among the accounts held by the University are: Account Number 40-131: A consolidated Investment account, established October 11, 1949; 40-197: Ford Foundation Grants, established September 21, 1956; 40-198: Ford Foundation Medical Grants, established October 11, 1956; 75-009: H.J. Heinz Sunday School Endowment, established May 20, 1924; 75-012: John Brindley Endowment for the School of Medicine; 40-125: Graduate School of Public Health, established October 11, 1949; 40-179: General Endowment for the Health Center, established February 15, 1954; 18-094: Consolidate Investment Mortgages, established October 11, 1949; 555-555: Combined Accounts; 127723: Consolidated Investment Fund on Account with Pittsburgh National Bank, established April 1, 1954; 8668: Mulhert Fellowship fund on account with Fidelity Trust Company Unnumbered Account for Building Fund
        These are the major accounts. There are a few others. These are entered by the name of the account. In some instances minutes of Finance Committee Meetings are found in the Statements. They are arranged chronologically.
      - General and endorsement account statements, April-December, 1949 (Box 5, Folder 57)
      - General and endorsement account statements, December 1949-February 1950 (Box 5, Folder 58)
      - General and endorsement account statements, May 1950 (Box 5, Folder 59)
      - General and endorsement account statements, February 1951 (Box 5, Folder 60)
      - General and endorsement account statements, September 1951 (Box 5, Folder 61)
      - General and endorsement account statements, November 1951 (Box 5, Folder 62)
      - General and endorsement account statements, September 1951 (Box 5, Folder 62)
      - General and endorsement account statements, February 1952 (Box 5, Folder 63)
      - General and endorsement account statements, May 1952 (Box 5, Folder 64)
      - General and endorsement account statements, August 1952 (Box 5, Folder 65)
      - General and endorsement account statements, September 1952 (Box 5, Folder 66)
      - General and endorsement account statements, November 1952 (Box 5, Folder 67)
      - General and endorsement account statements, February 1953 (Box 5, Folder 68)
      - General and endorsement account statements, May 1953 (Box 5, Folder 69)
      - General and endorsement account statements, September 1953 (Box 5, Folder 70)
      - General and endorsement account statements, October 1953 (Box 5, Folder 71)
      - General and endorsement account statements, December 1953 (Box 5, Folder 72)
      - General and endorsement account statements, January-March 1954 (Box 5, Folder 73)
      - General and endorsement account statements, April 1954 (Box 5, Folder 74)
      - General and endorsement account statements, June 1954 (Box 5, Folder 75)
      - General and endorsement account statements, October 1954 (Box 5, Folder 76)
      - General and endorsement account statements, December 1954 (Box 5, Folder 77)
      - General and endorsement account statements, March 1955 (Box 5, Folder 78)
      - General and endorsement account statements, June 1955 (Box 5, Folder 79)
      - General and endorsement account statements, October 1955 (Box 5, Folder 80)
      - General and endorsement account statements, February 1956 (Box 5, Folder 81)
      - General and endorsement account statements, May 1956 (Box 5, Folder 82)
      - General and endorsement account statements, May 1956 (Box 5, Folder 83)
      - General and endorsement account statements, 1957-1959 (Box 5, Folder 84)
      - General and endorsement account statements, 1959-1965 (Box 6, Folder 84a)
      - General and endorsement account statements, 1966-1967 (Box 6, Folder 85)
      - General and endorsement account statements, 1968 (Box 6, Folder 86)
      - General and endorsement account statement, 1968-1972 (Box 7, Folder 86a)
      - Statements of operation, 1966-1969 (Box 7, Folder 87)
      - Committee on Audit - Financial reports, 1955, 1956, 1958 (Box 7, Folder 88)
      - Committee on Audit - Financial reports, 1961, 1964, 1965 (Box 7, Folder 89)
      - Committee on Audit - Financial reports, 1968, 1970, 1972 (Box 7, Folder 90)
      - Committee on Audit - Financial statements of Price Waterhouse and Co., 1958, 1959 (Box 7, Folder 91)
      - Reports - A long term financing program for the University and the revision, 1961, 1963 (Box 7, Folder 92)
      - Reports, 1941-1961 (Box 7, Folder 93)
        Report of increase of university assets for land, building, and endowment during the last twenty years, 1941. Report on land, buildings, and equipment, July 31, 1961. Resolution to borrow from Mellon Bank to pay off the stadium bonds and build a student union and field house.
      - Investment correspondence financial reports, 1961, 1966 (Box 7, Folder 94)
        1961 report and the revision of the endowment fund, June 13, 1966
      - Investment correspondence financial reports, 1945-1971 (Box 7, Folder 95)
        Summary of security holdings, 1945. Restricted investments of the building fund, 1949. Restricted investments of current expendable funds, 1949. Restricted investments of endowment funds, 1949. Total endowment funds of the university, 1949. Analysis of major fund comprising the endowment fund, 1965. Analysis of endowment funds, 1955 and 1965. Analysis of temporary investments as of 1968. Review of investments 1968. Report of the Investment Committee, 1971.
      - Memoranda, 1949-1968 (Box 7, Folder 96)
        General provisions of state law regarding the investment of funds, 1949. Brevits compilation of securities held by various colleges and universities, 1958. Background of the Maurice Falk endowed professorship of politics, of the McEllory Professorship endowment fund, and the Carroll Amundson Endowed Professor of British History, 1965. Securities held by the university, 1969.
      - Minutes, 1968-1973 (Box 7, Folder 97-99)